I love theater.
احب المسرح
I love the idea that you can transform, become somebody else
احب فكرة التقمص لنصبح أفرادا آخرين
and look at life with a completely new perspective.
و نتأمل الحياة بمنظور جديد ومختلف تماما عنا
I love the idea that people will sit in one room for a couple of hours and listen.
احب فكرة جلوس الناس معا لعدة ساعات ليسمعوا
The idea that in that room at that moment,
فكرة كوننا في هذة الحجرة ؛ و في هذة اللحظة
everyone, regardless of their age, their gender, their race, their color, their religion,
الكل...بصرف النظر عن أعمارهم ؛ جنسهم ؛ عرقهم ؛ ألوانهم ؛ دينهم
comes together.
يجتمعوا
At that moment, we transcend space and time together.
في هذة اللحظة نحن نعبر المكان و الزمان معا
Theater awakens our senses and opens the door to our imagination.
المسرح ينشط أحاسيسنا و يفتح الباب لمخيلتنا
And our ability to imagine is what makes us explorers.
و قدرتنا على التخيل هي من يجعل منا مكتشفين
Our ability to imagine makes us inventors and creators and unique.
قدرتنا على التخيل تصنع منا مخترعين و مبتكرين و اصحاب قدرات فريدة
I was commissioned in 2003 to create an original show,
تم تكليفي في عام 2003 بابتكار عرض جديد
and began developing "Upwake."
فبدأت ببناء "أب ويك / شبه مستيقظ / استيقظ"
"Upwake" tells the story of Zero,
"اب ويك " يحكي قصة صفر
a modern-day business man, going to work with his life in a suitcase,
رجل أعمال عصري يتجه لعمله حاملا حياته في حقيبة اليدوية
stuck between dream and reality and not able to decipher the two.
حُشر بين الواقع و الحلم و لا يمكنه فك شفرة أى منهما
I wanted "Upwake" to have the same audiovisual qualities as a movie would.
أردت للعرض نفس المؤثرات الصوتية و السمعية التي تستخدم في السينما
And I wanted to let my imagination run wild.
و أردت لمخيلتي الجموح
So I began drawing the story that was moving in my head.
لذا بدأت برسم الحدوتة التي تدور برأسي
If Antoine de Saint-Exupery, the author of "The Little Prince," were here,
لو كان انطوان دى سانت اكسبيرى مؤلف قصة " الأمير الصغير " هنا
he would have drawn three holes inside that box
لرسم ثلاث فجوات داخل هذا الصندوق
and told you your sheep was inside.
و أخبرك أنك تمتلك جميع أدواتك بالداخل
Because, if you look closely enough, things will begin to appear.
لأنك لو اقتربت و دققت ستتضح لك الأمور
This is not a box; these are the renderings of my imagination
هذا ليس مجرد صندوق ؛ إنه تداعيات خيالي الجامح
from head to paper to screen to life.
من العقل للورق للشاشة للحياة
In "Upwake" buildings wear suits, Zero tap dances on a giant keyboard,
في " شبه مستيقظ" ...ترتدي المباني بدل.....يرقص "صفر" فوق لوحة مفاتيح عملاقة
clones himself with a scanner, tames and whips the computer mice,
ينسخ نفسه باستخدام ماسح ضوئي و يروض فأر الكمبيوتر و يضربه بالسياط
sails away into dreamscape from a single piece of paper and launches into space.
يبحر بعيدا في أراضي الأحلام مندفعا من قطعة ورق وحيدة و ينطلق نحو الفضاء
I wanted to create environments that moved and morphed like an illusionist.
أردت ابتكار بيئة تتحرك و تتشكل كوهم و ضباب
Go from one world to another in a second.
الانتقال السريع من عالم لأخر في اللاوقت
I wanted to have humor, beauty, simplicity and complexity
أردت جمال و حس فكاهة و بساطة و تعقيد
and use metaphors to suggest ideas.
و استخدم الاستعارات لاقترح أفكارا
At the beginning of the show, for example, Zero deejays dream and reality.
في بداية العرض ...يتلاعب "صفر" بالواقع و الافتراض كاسطوانة موسيقية سهلة التحريك
Technology is an instrument that allowed me to manifest my visions
التكنولوجيا أداة تمكنني من عرض رؤيتي
in high definition, live, on stage.
بجودة عالية ....كبث مباشر على المسرح
So today, I would like to talk to you about the relationship
لذا اليوم أريد أن اتحدث معكم عن العلاقة
between theater and technology.
بين المسرح و التكنولوجيا
Let's start with technology.
لنبدأ بالتكنولوجيا
(Fuse blowing)
صوت قابس كهربائي يتم فصله
All right. Let's start with theater.
حسنا.....لنبدأ بالمسرح
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Buzzing)
صوت طنين نحلة
(Click, click, bang)
(كليك, كليك, بانج)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
"Upwake" lasts 52 minutes and 54 seconds.
يستغرق العرض 52 دقيقة و 54 ثانية
I project 3D animation on all the four surfaces of the stage
اقدم رسوم متحركة ثلاثية الابعاد على جدران المسرح الأربع
which I interact with.
و التي اتفاعل معها
The use of animation and projection was a process of discovery.
كان استخدام الرسوم المتحركة و جهاز البث عملية اكتشاف مستمر
I didn't use it as a special effect, but as a partner on stage.
فلم استخدمها كتأثير خاص منفصل عن الأداء ...لكن كشريك مسرحي
There are no special effects in "Upwake," no artifice.
لا تأثيرات خاصة و لا حيل بالعرض
It's as lavish and intricate as it is simple and minimal.
فهو سخي و مركب بقدر ما هو بسيط و صغير
Three hundred and forty-four frames, four and a half years and commissions later,
344 اطار....4 سنين و نصف ...و لاحقا لجان خاصة به
what started as a one person show became a collaborative work
العرض الذي بدأ كأداء لفرد واحد تطور لعمل جماعي متعاون
of nineteen most talented artists.
وصلوا ل 19 من أكثر الفنانين موهبة
And here are some excerpts.
و إليكم بعض المقتطفات
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
So this is, relatively, a new show that we're now beginning to tour.
لذا فهو نسبيا عرض جديد بدأ الآن في التجوال
And in Austin, Texas,
في اوسطن, تكساس
I was asked to give small demonstrations in schools during the afternoon.
طُلب مني تقديم عروض صغيرة في بعض المدراس في فترة بعد الظهر
When I arrived at one of the schools, I certainly did not expect this:
و عندما وصلت لمدرسة منهم ....حقيقة لم أتوقع هذا العدد
Six hundred kids, packed in a gymnasium, waiting.
600 طفل اجتمعوا في صالة الألعاب منتظرين
I was a little nervous performing without animation, costume -- really -- and make-up.
كنت متوترة قليلا حيث أنني كنت أقدم بدون أى رسوم متحركة , ملابس خاصة, و حتى بدون مكياج
But the teachers came to me afterward and told me
لكن المعلمين جاوءني بعد ذلك و أخبروني
they hadn't seen the kids that attentive.
أنهم لم يروا الأطفال متحمسين هكذا من قبل
And I think the reason why is that I was able to use their language and their reality
و اعتقد أن سبب هذا التواصل هو أننى استطعت استخدام لغتهم و واقعهم
in order to transport them into another.
مع القدرة على التلاعب بهذا الواقع و تحويله لآخر
Something happened along the way.
شيء حدث خلال الرحلة
Zero became a person and not just a character in a play.
"صفر" أصبح أنسانا و ليس مجرد شخصية في مسرحية
Zero does not speak, is neither man nor woman.
"صفر لا يتحدث ليس رجل و لا إمرأة
Zero is Zero, a little hero of the 21st Century,
صفر هو صفر.....بطل صغير من أبطال القرن الواحد و العشرين
and Zero can touch so many more people than I possibly could.
و يمكن لصفر التأثير في العديد من الناس أكثر من استطاعتي أنا
It's as much about bringing new disciplines inside this box
لديه القدرة على استحضار الكثير من الضوابط و الفنيات داخل صندوق المسرح المتخيل
as it is about taking theater out of its box.
بنفس القدرة على إستخراج المسرح خارج حدود الصندوق للكون الأوسع
As a street performer, I have learned that everybody wants to connect.
كمؤدية أدوار تمثل في الشارع.....تعلمت أننا جميعا نريد التواصل
And that usually, if you're a bit extraordinary, if you're not exactly of human appearance,
و كالعادة....لو كنت و لو على قدر ضئيل من الغير عادية ....لو لم تكن تشبه تماما الانسان العادي
then people will feel inclined to participate and to feel out loud.
ستسهل على الناس رغبتهم في التواصل سينفعلوا معك بسهولة و بدون حرج
It's as though you made something resonate within them.
كأنك تصدر رنين يتماشى مع رغبتهم في التواصل
It's as though the mystery of the person they're interacting with and connecting
كأن سر الشخصية الغير إعتيادية التي يتفاعلون معها
allows them to be themselves just a bit more.
يدفعهم ليكونوا أنفسهم بقدر ما هي غير نفسها
Because through your mask, they let theirs go.
لأن خلال القناع يتركون لأنفسهم الانطلاق بعيدا عن الحدود الاجتماعية المعروفة التي قد تقيد انفعالاتهم
Being human is an art form.
كوننا آدميين يعد شكلا فنيا
I know theater can improve the quality of people's lives,
اؤمن بقدرة المسرح في تحين جودة الحياة
and I know theater can heal.
أؤمن بقدرته الشفائية
I've worked as a doctor clown in a hospital for two years.
عملت كمهرج في المستشفيات لمدة سنتين
I have seen sick kids and sad parents and doctors
تعاملت مع أطفال مرضى و آباء و أطباء حزانى
be lifted and transported in moments of pure joy.
الضحكة غيرتهم و احالتهم لدقيقة من المتعة الخالصة
I know theater unites us.
اؤمن بقدرة المسرح على تجميعنا و اتحادنا
Zero wants to engage the generation of today and tomorrow,
"صفر" يحلم بربط أجيال اليوم و الغد
tell various stories through different mediums.
يحكي قصص عدة عبر وسائط مختلفة
Comic books. Quantum physics video games.
كتب رسوم متحركة.....ألعاب فيديو
And Zero wants to go to the moon.
و صفر يريد السفر للقمر
In 2007, Zero launched a green campaign,
في عام 2007 أطلق صفر حملة خضراء
suggesting his friends and fans to turn off their electricity
اقترح على أصدقائه و محبيه غلق الكهرباء
every Sunday from 7:53 to 8:00 p.m.
كل أحد من 7:53 لل 8:00 مساء لمدة سبع دقائق فقط لا غير
The idea is simple, basic. It's not original,
الفكرة بسيطة أساسية و ليست بدعة
but it's important, and it's important to participate.
لكنها هامة و ضرورى علينا المشاركة
There is a revolution.
إنها ثورة
It's a human and technological revolution.
إنها ثورة انسان و تكنولوجيا
It's motion and emotion.
إنها حركة و شعور
It's information.
معلومات
It's visual. It's musical. It's sensorial.
مرئية ...موسيقية ....و حسية
It's conceptual. It's universal. It's beyond words and numbers.
تصورية ...عالمية.....تتخطى الأحرف و الأرقام
It's happening.
إنها ببساطة تحدث....
The natural progression of science and art
إنها تطور طبيعي للعلم و الفن
finding each other to better touch and define the human experience.
لتواصل أفضل بين الجميع و اعادة تعريف للخبرات الانسانية
There is a revolution in the way that we think,
إنها ثورة منهجية التفكير
in the way that we share, and the way that we express our stories,
التي نتبعها في التقاسم والتعبير عن حكاياتنا
our evolution.
إنها تطورنا
This is a time of communication, connection and creative collaboration.
هذا وقت التواصل و الارتباط و التعاون المبدع
Charlie Chaplin innovated motion pictures
ابتكر تشارلي تشابلن صور تتحرك
and told stories through music, silence, humor and poetry.
ليحكى قصص بالموسيقى و الصمت بالدعابة و الشعر
He was social, and his character, The Tramp, spoke to millions.
كان اجتماعيا.... شخصيته شخصية المتشرد تحدثت للملايين
He gave entertainment, pleasure and relief to so many human beings
قدم امتاع...سعادة....شفاء للعديد من البشر
when they needed it the most.
في الوقت الذي احتاجوا إليها بشدة
We are not here to question the possible; we are here to challenge the impossible.
نحن لسنا هنا لنسأل عن الممكن لكننا هنا لنتحدى المستحيل
In the science of today, we become artists.
في علم اليوم اصبحنا فنانين
In the art of today, we become scientists.
و في فن اليوم أصبحنا علماء
We design our world. We invent possibilities.
نصمم عالمنا...نبتكر إمكانياتنا
We teach, touch and move.
نعلم ...نلمس....نتحرك
It is now that we can use the diversity of our talents
الآن يمكننا استغلال تنوع المواهب
to create intelligent, meaningful and extraordinary work. It's now.
لنبتكر عمل ذكي معبر و خارق للعادة....و هو التفوق
(Ringing)
(رنين)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)